Hey everyone, it's Richard. You're
watching the Plain Bagel, your number
one tariff news channel here with a big
update. As you've probably heard, the US
Supreme Court has officially ruled that
Donald Trump's tariffs brought under the
International Emergency Economic Powers
Act, or AIPA for short, are illegal,
upholding a lower court ruling and
forcing the White House to lift all
previously imposed tariffs under this
law. A pretty big update to the global
trade war timeline and one that was
celebrated by many online who saw this
as dealing a meaningful blow to Trump's
trade tariff agenda, effectively
unraveling what's been one of Trump's
favorite tools for international
relations and negotiations.
At least that was the case for a solid
couple of hours until the president came
out with a fiery press conference
highlighting that not only had the
Supreme Court failed in stopping its
tariffs, but he would actually be coming
back with even more tariffs, seemingly
in retaliation, I guess, uh, with the
president the same day as the ruling
announcing a new temporary 10% tariff
against most other countries and later
on Saturday announcing that this rate
would be increasing to 15%. Albeit, as
of the time of posting, we've only so
far seen the 10% tariff go into effect
on Tuesday, February 24th. So,
naturally, it all raises a number of
questions. Who's impacted here? What's
the deal with these new tariffs? And
what's going to happen to the estimated
$175 billion of tariff revenue that's
already been collected that's now been
deemed illegal? Well, that's what we'll
cover in today's video. in addition to
what laws the president might use in the
future to reintroduce tariffs and
increase levies further beyond the 10 or
15% we've seen so far. And we'll start
by going through the Supreme Court
ruling itself. You can see that the case
is Learning Resources versus Trump,
President of the United States. Learning
Resources is actually an Illinois based
uh toy company that brought this case
against the White House, albeit the case
was actually combined with another
similar case brought by the liquor
company VOS Elections and 12 US states,
which is why you can see multiple
plaintiffs here. And in the case, the
plaintiffs alleged and the Supreme Court
justices upheld that AIPA does not
authorize the president to impose
tariffs. AIPA is a 1977 law that among
other things allows the president a
number of powers to restrict
transactions and trade in the presence
of a quote unusual and extraordinary
threat. Essentially providing a way for
the president to bypass congressional
approval in the face of a threat to
national security. However, the justices
ruled 6 to3 with three conservative
justices dissenting that while the
president has the power to block imports
and exports under this law, the power to
explicitly tax is not covered by these
powers and rests solely with Congress as
outlined in the Constitution. Something
that was supported by president with no
president having ever previously imposed
tariffs under AIPA. And the justices
argued that Trump's tariffs violated the
major questions doctrine uh which
requires that actions by the
government's executive branch of
significant consequence be clearly
authorized by Congress rather than
through ambiguous language. In other
words, because AIPA doesn't explicitly
give Trump the power to tariff
countries, and because Trump has been
meaningfully leaning on this law,
handing out tariffs like Oprah Winfrey
with how he's been making sure everyone
gets one, these actions should require
congressional approval. With the
justices indicating, quote, "The
president must point to clear
congressional authorization to justify
his extraordinary assertion of that
power. He cannot." Now, as for which
tariffs are impacted here, the justices
highlighted two main sets of levies. The
first being the fentanyl linked tariffs
Trump first announced early in his term
against China, Mexico, and Canada.
Specifically, the 10% tariff on Chinese
goods, 25% tariff on Mexican goods, and
the heightened 35% tariff on Canadian
goods. And the second set are the more
broadly reaching country specific
reciprocal tariffs uh that Trump first
announced on April 2nd or the so-called
liberation day with this being inclusive
of the many updated tariffs that came
afterwards. Meaning that any of the
countries that saw their names appear on
those bristle board posters and beyond
have now seen those tariffs effectively
erased. Meaning that we finally seen
justice for the Herd and McDonald Island
penguins who have been wrongly targeted
by tariffs from the beginning. Now,
importantly, that does leave other
tariffs unaffected here. Uh, we will
continue to see the sectoral tariffs
brought under section 232 of the trade
expansion act of 1962, which if you
recall includes levies on most steel and
aluminum, auto parts, certain copper
products, soft wood and timber,
furniture, and semiconductor imports.
And these will continue to impact a lot
of countries. You can see from this map
that even the sectoral tariffs alone
still capture a lot of America's global
trade partners. However, according to
Reuters, these other nonaipa tariffs
only made up about a third of the
revenue generated from Trump's tariffs
in the last quarter of 2025,
demonstrating that this ruling still
strikes down the lion's share of Trump's
tariffs with Pen Wharton budget model
economists estimating that AIPA tariffs
provided 175 billion in revenue for the
US government since their
implementation. Which brings us to the
question, what happens to this collected
$175 billion now that the tariffs that
raised this amount were deemed illegal?
Well, there still remains a pretty big
question mark there. While it's largely
expected that this ruling will compel
the US government to refund these
illegally collected levies, the ruling,
as highlighted by the dissenting
opinion, says nothing about how the
government should go about doing so.
essentially leaving the issue to lower
courts like the US Court of
International Trade to decide, which
means that we're probably in for years
of further litigation before we see any
money returned here, with in fact Trump
and members of his administration
suggesting that they'll be fighting the
matter in court. And of course, it's
very unlikely we see a fair repayment of
the tariffs here. While Trump long
maintained that it would be foreign
companies who would be paying
predominantly for these tariffs here and
there is some truth to these companies
covering some of the costs by lowering
their own prices. That tone is obviously
going to change now that it's time to
pay the amounts back. And while US
consumers bore the brunt of tariff costs
via the passalong price hikes, any
refund we do see is likely to go
predominantly to importing companies to
whom the tariff fees were explicitly
charged when importing goods. And even
then, because getting a refund will
likely require some sort of application
or potentially even uh fighting the
matter in court, smaller companies who
don't have the resources for these
things are going to be pretty
disadvantaged when compared to larger
companies like FedEx, for example, who
just this week became the first large US
company to file a lawsuit following this
ruling for the reclamation of tariffs,
with a number of other companies,
including Costco, having also sued the
government prior to the judgment. And
while the idea of paying a dividend
tariff to a bunch of people has been
floated in the past, that would likely
require congressional approval and would
be unlikely to meet the requirements of
a reimbursement here. But hey, while you
might not get a tariff refund here for
the higher prices you've been paying,
you can rest assured that at least the
large corporations are taken care of.
Now, in terms of the broader impact of
this ruling, there's obviously a mix of
factors here. While the returning of
tariff funds could be a positive for the
economy, it does leave the government in
an awkward position with its budget. Uh
given that tariffs were a key offsetting
force to Trump's higher deficits under
the one big beautiful bill, the IPA
tariffs alone that have been collected
represent about 10% of the 2025 fiscal
budget deficit. And obviously it's up in
the air how much tariff revenue will be
raised in the future. And there's a
pretty big impact on price levels. The
budget laba eel estimates that the
complete elimination of these tariffs
would reduce the average effective
tariff rate faced by consumers from
16.9% to 9.1% and cut the expected price
level inflation from tariffs in half
from 1.2% to 0.6%. With the price impact
being even more significant when you
dive into specific product categories.
However, as mentioned, tariffs are
seemingly not going away and may in fact
uh increase as Trump has seemingly
alluded to with Trump quickly replacing
the illegal tariffs with a temporary 10%
across the board levy under section 122
of the Trade Act of 1974. A section that
permits the president to impose tariffs
of up to 15% for up to 150 days to
address large and serious balance of
payments deficits. uh with that simply
meaning any circumstance where the
country is sending more money abroad
than it is receiving uh something that
doesn't require a formal investigation
but Trump could argue regardless uh
given the trade deficits the country
does face with the US buying more
imports than it exports now importantly
while the tariffs are being described as
a baseline tariff here the white house
did include a number of exemptions to
this new levy uh with this including
certain critical minerals and metals
energy and energy products s natural
resources and fertilizers that cannot be
produced efficiently in the US, certain
agricultural products, pharmaceuticals
and pharmaceutical ingredients, certain
electronics, passenger and other
vehicles, certain aerospace products,
information materials, donations in a
company baggage, anything already
subject to the sectoral section 232
tariffs we mentioned earlier, and
finally any duty-free goods under the US
MCA agreement with Canada and Mexico or
textiles and apparel under the Dominican
Republic Central America free trade
agreement. So, you can see that there
are some meaningful carveouts here. Now
for Canada specifically, the change in
tariffs we have seen is a bit less
important. Even though the country is
seeing its general tariff rate fall from
35% to 10%. The country was already
sending the vast majority of its
products tariff-free to the US under the
USMCA agreement. And for everyone else,
as mentioned, the tariff is only
temporary with it requiring
congressional approval to be extended
beyond that first 150 days, which seems
very unlikely given that the House of
Representatives amid all of this has
already voted to cancel some of Trump's
tariffs, specifically around Canada. And
Congress faces upcoming midterm
elections in November, just a few months
after these tariffs expire. So, with
tariffs being fairly unpopular in the
US, that might not be something
politicians look to support. But that
brings us to what comes after this first
150 days. And while some might have
their fingers crossed that it might be
the end of of global tariffs from the
United States, that does seem very
unlikely. Uh there are many different
avenues through which Trump can reimpose
tariffs here. The first of which, of
course, being those sectoral tariffs
that were already seen under section
232. While these do require an
investigation by the Department of
Commerce to demonstrate the national
security risk, the president has now
bought himself 150 days to sort through
which sectors he wants to impact here.
And even beyond the sector tariffs,
there are a number of ways through which
Trump could impose further levies. With
in his response to the ruling, Trump
specifically highlighting three other
statutes with which he could impose
further tariffs. The first two also come
from the trade act of 1974. Uh the first
being section 2011 which allows the US
to impose product specific tariffs when
increased imports are causing serious
injury or the threat thereof to domestic
producers and section 301 which allows
tariffs when trade deals are being
violated or a country is putting an
unjustifiable burden or restriction on
US commerce with both of these sections
requiring a formal investigation
something Trump actually announced for
the latter section along with his
announcement of the temporary 10%
tariffs. Then there's section 338 of the
tariff act of 1930 whereby the president
can impose country specific tariffs of
up to 50% in cases where a country
unreasonably discriminates against US
trade. A section that doesn't seemingly
require a formal review, but one that
would likely face legal challenges if
used in this sort of broad-based
approach given some of the unclear
details with the law. So, while some may
have hoped that the Supreme Court ruling
finally signaled the end of Trump's
tariff tirade, to his point uh with his
rant after the ruling, there are many
other tools in Trump's arsenal for
keeping tariffs in place. But that's not
to say the update doesn't matter. The
ruling is still a pretty big blow to
Trump's tariff agenda and foreign
policy. For one, while the president has
threatened higher tariffs here
currently, the ruling has reduced
tariffs pretty meaningfully for a number
of countries. Uh, previously we saw most
countries facing at least 10% tariffs
with other countries facing AIPA tariffs
as high as 50%. However, those rates
have now all been replaced with a
baseline 10% across the board, which for
some countries like Brazil meaningfully
decreases the levy paid on their
exports. It's also led to some
discontent from countries who have
already made trade deals with the US to
lower their trade tariffs. Countries
like the UK and the entirety of the
European Union have not so far been
granted any carve out in this new update
and seemingly now faced the same rate as
everyone else, including the potentially
higher 15% rate despite making
concessions around purchases,
investments, and tariffs with the
European Union actually delaying its own
deal ratification as a result of this
uncertainty. Now, US trade
representatives have reassured countries
that the US will be sticking to its
previously negotiated deals. But given
Trump's track record of pulling 180s on
his own trade deals, we could see
countries discouraged in their
negotiations with Trump if there's
concerns that he might go full Darth
Vader and just start changing terms on
people.
>> I am altering the deal. Pray I don't
alter it any further. But above all
else, while Trump again does have other
tools in his arsenal, the ruling does
take away one of the president's
favorite big sticks here. Uh, previously
Trump had been pretty quick to either
threaten or impose tariffs under AIPA
for a slew of at times seemingly
unrelated or frivolous issues with Trump
imposing AIPA tariffs against Brazil
seemingly mostly because of the
country's prosecution of former
president Gier Bolsinaro in Switzerland
because in a phone call with their
former president, he quote didn't really
like the way she talked to us. And of
course, here in Canada, we've seen that
firsthand with the country being
threatened with a slew of tariffs for
everything from the country's planned
implementation of a digital services tax
to its airing of an anti-tariff ad that
relayed a direct quote of Ronald Reagan
on the negative impact tariffs have on
the economy. But now, it's going to be
harder for the president to impose
tariffs on a whim like he's done in the
past, with any future tariffs likely to
require a more formal review. So, while
Trump can certainly threaten future
tariffs as leverage, something we've
already seen in the midst of this
decision with Trump warning countries
not to play games around the trade deals
and warning countries during his State
of the Union address to stick to their
negotiated deals if they didn't want to
face his renewed eye under different
tariff laws. The ruling does mitigate
his ability to just bludgeon a country
with levies whenever they do, say, or
sound some way he doesn't like. So,
we'll have to wait and see how this
ultimately impacts the country's foreign
relations. Uh whether we see countries
stick to the tone of their former and
ongoing negotiations or if we see more
push back and frustration amid the
changing circumstances within the US.
Trump could also use all this as an out
for the policy leading up to the coming
midterm elections. But with the
president once again sharing his vision
of replacing a substantial portion of
income taxes with tariffs during his
State of the Union address, we haven't
seen any indication that he'd be backing
away from this policy. But again, we'll
ultimately have to wait and see. Thanks
for watching. I hope you found this
video helpful. If you did, please do
make sure to like, subscribe, all that
good stuff. It does help the channel
tremendously. And let me know your
thoughts on the update from the Supreme
Court. Are you happy with the ruling? Do
you view it as pointless and expensive
given the need to now reimburse tariffs
here? Any and all thoughts, welcome down
below. Thanks again for joining and as
always
be safe out